[Music]
hippocrates the father of western
medicine believe that all diseases begin
in the gut
of course he also thought women were
hysterical because of their wandering
uterus
so much for ancient medical wisdom
but something like constipation can have
a major negative impact and physical
mental and social well-being gets often
overlooked in health care this may be
because poop talk is taboo
but can have a severe influence on their
everyday living both psychologically
physically constipation can hurt causing
abdominal discomfort and pain straining
hard stool and frequent bowel movements
bloating and nausea
no wonder laxatives are among the most
commonly used drugs
most are safe when used judiciously and
intermittently but because the frequency
of their use they do end up being one of
the most common causes of adverse drug
reactions
perhaps treatment should instead address
the underlying problems such as lack of
dietary fiber
you probably don't need a meta-analysis
to demonstrate that dietary fiber can
obviously increase stool frequency
populations in most western countries
must be considered by world standards to
be almost
universally constipated
here
it's an epidemic among the elderly but
simply not a problem among those
centering their diets around fiber-rich
foods
where is fiber found this patient
summary in the ama's journal sums it up
with an illustration whole
unrefined plant foods
now for those of us smug and our intake
of fruits and vegetables
we need to realize that fruits and leafy
vegetables are the poorest whole food
sources of fiber why because they're 90
percent water right root vegetables have
more but the fiber superstars are
legumes beans beans flippies chickpeas
and lentils as well as whole grains
and gram per gram fruit fiber doesn't
seem to have the same effect it may take
25 grams of fruit fiber to double stool
output
something just 10 grams of whole grain
fiber or vegetable fiber can do
and that's not all fiber can do if you
eat some whole grain barley for supper
by the next morning your good gut
bacteria are having it for breakfast
releasing butyrate into our bloodstream
a compound that seems to exert broad
anti-inflammatory activities which could
help explain why significant decreases
in the prevalence of inflammation are
associated with increasing dietary fiber
intakes
check it out
and the highest group here was just
getting the minimum recommended daily
intake of fiber
so what if you have knee pain or
something you should eat more fiber rich
foods
we didn't know
until
now
dietary fiber intake in relation to knee
pain trajectory thousands of patients
were followed and
a high intake of dietary fiber which is
to say just the minimum recommended
intake was associated with a lower risk
of developing moderate or severe knee
pain over time and to framingham studies
found that higher fiber intake was
related to a lower risk of having
symptomatic osteoarthritis in the first
place
but wait don't a variety of diseases
have an inflammatory component
how about fiber consumption and
all-cause cardiovascular and cancer
mortality they found that compared to
those who consumed the least fiber those
who consumed the most had 23 percent
less cardiovascular disease mortality 17
lower risk of dying from cancer and 23
lower mortality from all causes put
together
unfortunately most persons in the united
states consume less than half the
recommended intake of dietary fiber
daily
these researchers suggest all sorts of
potential mechanisms for which fiber
could be life-saving from
improving cholesterol immune function
and blood sugar control but there also
may be more of a direct cause
if you ask people to bear down as if
they're straining on stool you can get a
rapid increase in intracranial pressure
pressure inside your skull and indeed if
you look at trigger factors for the
rupture of intracranial aneurysms if you
ask hundreds of people who had strokes
bleeds within their brains
one of the biggest trigger factors noted
was straining for defecation multiplying
risk seven-fold
[Music]
oh